I was
NY laboratory phone
Holloway
Talking to
Students
There's a call comes out of the blue
This young guy wanted to know it's the technology was ready to be commercialized
Lenny said the magic word
Awkward he says
I have
Access to some money that would allow us to
Let's get started
Okay
Where does the money originate
I need sub
I'm not a junior member at
That's a venture capital firm
I want to
To look up
What venture-capital mentally
Heard of it before
Chris Burgess willing to risk everything
Street Fighter we didn't know we were doing Silicon Valley
Cisco flooring company
The rest is history I don't know how to write a business plan I can only tell you how we
I will you read them and we started the back and if the numbers are big we look at the front
Front see what kind of business it is
You have to look at the way conventional wisdom works and abandon it
No one has ever accused me of under-estimating
Myself
Jobs and Wozniak
Came up to see me
National Treasure
He is so visionary
And so bright
I had the fire ago
These men didn't always wheel such influence in power
In the beginning
We barely knew what they were doing
50 years ago they were just young guys from modest means
Who thought they could help build Innovative companies
This is a story of a
12 man who stirred up a revolution in science and technology
Cuz they saw opportunity
Where others only song risk
Venture capital
I don't think I thought of it
First
But I don't know anyone use the term before I did
Back in the spring of 90
1957 Arthur Rock was just a junior Banker on Wall Street for then one day and
An unsolicited letter arrived at the office
The letter was unusual and no one else has brokerage firm knew what to do with it
It was a cry for help
Forever change the trajectory of Arthur rocks life
You got to be lucky
Everybody's can be lucky at some time or another
Thing I say is I was lucky day
He lucky early
The letter on Arthur rocks desk
I come from sinners in
A group of brilliant young men
Become known as the traitorous eight
We were young guys
Good bunch of young engineers and
And the scientists mostly
Working together to Shockley semiconductor
They were having a hard time with Shockley
And they were going to leave
It depends in deteriorated a chocolate lab
He was a very difficult person to work with
And a group of us started considering the possibility Lisa leaving so anyhow
Refrigerator
Does Prospectors news to introduce a group of senior scientists and engineers
Who have been working together it's Shockley semiconductor Laboratory
Cochlea just want to Nobel Prize
Was probably a little presumptuous others
I think we can push him aside
A group feeling a rose
To the effect that rather than leave one by one
Believe we are much more valuable to an employer as a group
Lease were
The resumes varies
Superior
Nice thought
Would you maybe there's something here
Something
More valuable than just to be an employee
Something that Arthur saw inspire
Fire him two step
How does ordinary roll is a Wall Street Banker
And that's when we met Arthur Rock
Arthur
Came out to meet with a group of us
And Arthur said
You want to start your own company I will find
Financing for you
So does this idea themselves nobody thought of starting their own company of those days
It was a new idea but it was a good one
At that time there was no Venture Capital so starting companies was new it wasn't of age
Innovative
Arthur Rock had to get creative about signing capital for the Traders 8
Is Bankhead contacts with Rich families at the Rockefellers in the Whitney's
But they weren't interested in backing a startup
All the way out in California
Made a list of companies
Exactly sat down with the Wall Street Journal
Looking for a company to ask to invest in these eight fellows in forming a new company
I think we have 35 companies
The attempt to start a new company might have ended then and there
With the traitorous eight returning to a job search
Arthur Rock admitting defeat
But then
Arthur received one last lead
We were pretty much at wit's end
And somebody suggested that I see your Sherman Fairchild
Sherman Fairchild
What's an entrepreneurial M self and also a very wealthy man
You right away shortly Pashto
Filippi's
And decided that
Fairchild
Cameron instrument
Would invest lie
Didn't half dollars we were looking for
Call myself The Accidental entrepreneur
With a 1.5 million Arthur raised the traitorous eight
Fairchild Semiconductor in Mountain View California
5 miles south of San Francisco
Fairchild was the first company to manufacture the sophisticated silicon chips
Ships that would power computers rockets and spacecraft Paving the way for
The high-tech AIDS in time the fruit orchards
Downing Fairchild
Which way to electronics companies
In the area would become famous as the Silicon Valley
Sand stayed together and formed
Fairchild semiconductor
Probably
Rapinoe silicon in Silicon Valley
Arthur rocket got Nets haste to something exciting insignificant
Wasn't the only one trying to figure out how to find young companies the road from Fairchild
Unfold businessmen were experimenting with their own version of venture-capital together
There were a group of us in San Francisco that used to get interested in small high-tech companies down the peninsula
There were
Take 5 listener
We all had jobs we
And other time her hands to we decide we just
We'll just make love together
We were just a bunch of young man in San Francisco who knew each other and respected each other what it was like was
I'm very close
Fraternity I guess I can use that word
Carefully
Table of six or eight for lunch
None of us got enough money to do an investment by ourselves
We had to have help
It one of us ran across the
Entrepreneur who is trying to start a company with
Invite him up for lunch and after lunch with mask him to step out onto the street corner for a while
Give us 10 minutes and would make up our mind as to whether we wanted to invest in his company or not
I don't remember that
We didn't do that
We're too classy to do that that's a little bit quick I think
By the way
But I asked him to go get a cup of coffee
Two members of the group even more than gather round a lunch take
Every 6 weeks
In 1962
Draper
All their personal savings
Quit their day jobs to form a partnership and hit the streets
H & I
Each got a Pontiac least
And I am when a rat Henda knocked on doors and
If it sounded like
ABC Electronics
Then we go in after Presidency down and tell her
What are you doing what are you doing Venture tell what's that
My kids go to school what is your dad doing my dad's actually somebody as a firearm ID as a banker
And where's your dad you'll always Adventure capitalist
Damn you do actually you know
We were just stumbling around trying to figure out what to do
But we just knew that if we got involved with good people and good markets we could probably do over company
Growing companies create companies your helping to create something
Something for nothing
Existed before
And quite a large community got sustenance that wouldn't have existed unless you would gotten together
Together with this entrepreneur and his team and helped him
Along the way
Unscrupulous gambits a good formula
Everyone was sharing in the profits and success at these
Is Fletchling companies
Fairchild
It was a different story
Who was an imperfect
Vehicle
I joined
End of the 50
Part of the traitorous eight
Fairchild is owned by a corporation
An Eastman Corporation and the sense of division of equity
Was both unknown to them and repugnant
All of the East Coast companies
Had this
Hierarchy
They didn't understand
About
Shipping options to Aldi employees
The way west coast startups so if it to do
So the people in Fairchild
Including me
Are any kinds of significant ownership position
Then the early sixties
People began leaving Fair
Fairchild
To set up
Startups
And to begin to participate in what piece
What people
Correctly realize was
This was going to be something special
Meanwhile
Banker's desk New York
Well I'd wanted to do more of these
Venture Capital typed
The bunny was holding the east
And this
The scientist who would moved
From the East to the West
Cannoli ideas
So I saw a great opportunity and free
Bringing face cost money up
Stacking these people in other West Coast
Go West Young Man
In 1961 Arthur Rock raised $5000000 from East Coast investors
San Francisco
Start his own Venture Capital firm
He found a partner in Tommy Davis
Food in managing Investments for California oil company
Listen Rock quickly players in town
Funding a series of hue
Hugely successful technology company
Silicon Valley Community of the 1960s
It was only a matter of time before
Before Arthur Rockwood once again cross paths with the traitorous eight
Stock options independent
Inspire sealock start their own companies
It's two most important founders
Remain loyal to their company until May of 1968
Fairchild
East Coast management metastable mistake
Logical internal candidate
Do Visa next CEO
But they decided if we're going to look on the outside
Does that change the whole ball game
Noise filter
I'm going to leave are you interested
So I said okay
Let's do it
They need to expand and sing and they called me see whether I'd be interested
I came to be with no business plan
Other than what date
Verbally
Said they wanted to do
Usher said he needed something to talk to potential investors with just to give p
We wrote A business plan it was one page
Double-spaced Neva set
I just says we were going to make things out of silicon and some interesting electronic devices
Oh I said general terms ever going to make memories
It has lots of typos and I do Bob type hurt himself
It's not a very profound document but it is really kind of cute
So how much money do you need
It makes it two and a half million dollars and I said okay
What percentage is a company do you think you'll be happy giving up for two and a half million dollars
They thought so we'll help out a half
That's fine
And within a day and a half I can raise it to
Two and a half million dollars
Intel opened its doors in July of 68 and Arthur Ross Park
Partnership with its founders
Was only just beginning
Arthur was our chairman of the board in those days
It's been a lot of time there
Venture capitalist to write the check
Is that is an all we do
Writing a check is easy
Attendance
Staff meetings are there ask good questions was on the phone to him a lot
The next one board member offer advice planning
Interviewed a lot of people all of pieces of Ameriprise
I just spoke with
What I consider common sense
Does a table
Even measures wife there
Gave us guidance
When not to go public as well as wendigo public
I was very involved
It was all due to Intel.
Wasn't do to me
We went public
The same day that play
Playboy Enterprises web public
At the same price
A few years later one of the analysts
The market has spoken this memories over memories 12:50
Shortly after Arthur Rock went out on his own
Profound
Young investment manager
Now that you would mr. Davis her
We separate to find a younger partner do it all over again
And I said
I never
I mean with the light bulb
And I sat down and wrote him a long hand letter
And I never had ever done anything like this before
Probably Monday
I do telephone call mr. rocks on the line I said really
6 letter was very intriguing
He's just generally knowledgeable in on the same
Channel wish I was
And I found out later that there are over 1,000
The article
The Arthur had a handwriting expert
Analyze my letter
It's so deaf bunny so that's how I got an adventure business
Well you know there are no
Firm rules in the Venture Capital business
SEPTA there are no firm
No firm rules
Did you have any problems in convincing your colleagues
Yeah they thought I was out of my mind though
On this one
By the early 70s
Fired by the success were at The Rock
More members of the lunch group
Quit their day jobs and set up their own Venture funds
Read Dennis gave notice to his boss and American Express
You said are you sure that's what you want to do
I said Bill I've never been so sure of anything at all my life
Chevelle
We really don't want you to go but if you're determined to go you all to take some of our money with you
Laughs with gave us the impetus to start
Institutional Venture Associates
I potentially so profitable it was attracting people outside of Finance
Silicon Valley engineers
Eugene Kleiner Perkins form what would become one of the most successful Venture firms of all time
Well I started
Got into Venture Chapel by the back door
I was working for the Hewlett-Packard
When I had an idea for
Foray
Radically improve
And then I started the company
To manufacture the lasers
Worms all over I realized NE
I had been a venture capitalist
I put up the management
So then when I met Gene Kleiner who had
Left
Fairchild
We were both planning to go into the Venture Capital business
And we
Realize we complemented each other I mean I'm pretty intense in high strung and Gene was
Comonfort williams.az soothing Viennese accent
Eugene was just brilliant he was fun to be with
Murder once remodeled entrepreneur
And after you left us
You trust him
And Janine said
I would trust him
With my
My money
And that's how it started
We hung up our shingle
Nothing hat
The phone didn't ring we had a part-time secretary and we called out nobody called
Call them
We saw some deals
Then we did some deals
We lost money
In our original deal
I'll mention them even though they were very embarrassing
The most notorious in the maybe the fun
Was it coming coldsnow job which was the team to convert
Motorcycles into snowmobiles and
Which I actually worked and it was a lot of fun
One of the fuel crisis
Land is about the time we were ready
To go into production in
We couldn't get this to
Distributors
So Eugene and I thought you know this is not working
We've got to do something
Differently
Kalamazoo huge risk for clareburt
If Tim has failed up they would have never been a second Smiley forget Sivan
I think it was 33
That was young
Interns
People starting companies
But there weren't a lot of people starting companies
Ultimate reboot
Bruce smart guy
Very impressive
She had this idea Wichita
Not the technical Pro
Copart of apathy
Need
For a truly fault-tolerant computer
A computer
It would never fail
At that time for instance the
What's the New York Stock Exchange
I fell about
Everyday or every other day
And something would go wrong in it
It would destroy data
People knew the pro
The problem but they didn't have a solution
So just think of any credit checking Airline reservations pay
Banking
All Financial things on strip
All Communications
All kinds of thing
Or it's just not acceptable to have
The computer go down
We knew Tom and I knew
That if we could fill
Figure out a different kind of computer architecture
To solve this problem that we could create a big company
The problem was IBM
At 1 the Mainframe battle and 74
And
There was an article that said there would never be a new computer come
Never that was 74 and the
Cover was a picture of a short
And IBM was eating up here work company
When you think about
What
Decisions are being made
You got IV I'm wiping up GE
Siemens
So it would be easy not to want to go after that right
So you have to be brave
I mean you have to see it
And you have to be brave
And being brave is
One thing
You got to say about time
You got to look to get money from strong people because weak people don't invest into
Tough times
But that's when most of the big winners are created
Well first of all we didn't want to
Be the only backers
Backers of Tandem
We tried
To raise venture capital I made the trip back east
I remember
The first time we gave the pitch
Jimmy was
Straight out of
Texas
The real character
I didn't think you'd go over very well on Wall Street
He had to take any bus suit
He probably shared that
I'd literally took him to Brooks
Shoes socks the
He always say that
I forget what he said but
He could buy the suit but that still didn't help
Took it back
Wall Street in the Christophers thingy
That is not how I looked
I'm dressed
Tom was a
Hello more sophisticated than May
But we didn't get the money
Untried management
Unlikely idea
Most people
Would not have thought
Thought this was going to be a big winner
But I felt strongly enough about tannin
Even if we had to put up all of the money
We would do it
And then finally
Last minute
Johnson put in a small investment
I like to think that
Cub Scout my presence would be helpful in raising money elsewhere
It ratified our concept
I would credible in those days
I'm standing here next to a beautiful Tanner computer I think everyone recognizes this
Fine
Computer
Pittsburgh is a long time
Pick up that first order
The first customer
Was Citibank
When we got the first order and the computers
Performed as
Expected even better
The girls took off and became explosive
We went
725 fifteen hundred million two hundred million
Own up to a billion and we were fortune 500K
Company in
You use a tablet computer
Pretty much anytime you use your credit
When I started in the Venture business
It never occurred to me
That we would have multiple fun
Funds that Woody
Easily exceed a billion dollars
I got into the business somewhat fortuitously
When I
Made the decision
Decision
I had already put
Put in 13 years
Working in
Real companies
Don Valentine decided to train his connections
Semiconductor
Electric industry
In search of capital
To start a Venture van
We went to Steve
A guy at Solomon Brothers
And the said you know
I've listened to the pitch but
You didn't go to Harvard Business School
Guilty is
Is charged
Which is why you going to Business School
I said I went to Fairchild
Great business school
Startup company
Pioneer in a technology
Phenomenal leadership
Recognition
I said I don't need
To Business School
What I'm going to do
By Wall Street
Don Valentine found a mentor
Jenna Southern California mutual fund manager
Please take the money for Dawn's first
First Venture fund
I'm not interested in entrepreneurs
We'll do it our way
I'm not interested in entrepreneurs who think as a
The dress code
I'm interested in entrepreneurs who have a vision
Of doing something consequential
Preferably that becomes big
The most people that's something intimidating about the idea of interacting with a computer
But that is what's Happening Here
Atari
Had one of silicon Valley's absolutely larger-than-life personalities leading it
Nolan K Bushnell Bushnell with a young engineer
Working for game manufacturer cutting Associates when he decided to
The real thing that allowed me to start at re was I worked for nutting
And these guys couldn't find their butts with both hands I said you know I can run a company
And I won't make any of these things takes these idiots are doing
The first game Atari designed with
Took a prototype of the games
And placed it in a far
In Sunnyvale California morning customers were lined up outside clamor
A chance to play you put it on location turned a lot of money production
Directions sword in there seemed to be an insatiable appetite for the coin-operated game
From the outside batari look like a wildly successful company
Producing an endless stream of popular games
But there was one key Pro
Company was started with $250
And so we never had any money
If you're a hardware, you need a lot of capital for inventories the more successful
Successful the more you have to raise
Because
The more inventory you have the more customers or you're waiting to pay you
It takes a lot of capital
For hardware store.
In 1974
Pay for Atari was flirting with bankruptcy and desperately needed financial help
Nolan found the traditional channels off-limits
Traditional sense of things
Lend on acting spell do you have a house while give you a bargain do you have a car I'll give you a
Your loan on your car Nolan 10th no basis for a bank to be
Bank to be comfortable
I went through the factory and the smell of marijuana in
But I nearly knocked me to my knees
And I was
Gasping in
Coughing
Knows it what's the matter
I don't know what those people is smoking but it's not my brand
Passed on at REI
Surprising new products and development
Home pom Ataris engineers and discovered they can get the entire pop
Sounds the size of a shoebox
At the time playing video games at home for the Revolutionary concept
We showed on our play
Our plans for
Home games
He finally decided there was a business there
Giant market
He used to say you know the cleanup business you think it's big
This is you ain't seen nothing
Once we decide in 24
Refinance ettore
It was a matter of trying to fit
You figured out
Who else
Funds in those days
We're tiny
And in order for us
Start a company we have
To vary
Collegially
Together
I brought him other investors
How
It takes awhile to get you
Used to NOLA
And there's a story there about one of our meetings
For The Men Who Fidelity was sitting on
In a chair with his blue suit out of the rest of us were in the hot tub
Nolan was unrelentingly picking on him about his prudish Behavior he wouldn't get in the hot
With a controversial entrepreneur and no existing market for
Brown video games
Months went by the other investors remain on the fence about a tari
Himself took his home Punk
Prototype on the road in search of customers
Course we were young and felt that we could solve any problems came along and
You know selling and just
Toys R Us I can't be that hard
What then
I like to tell the story about
Taking the pong game to the toy fair in New York and selling nut
So we got let's try the
Television shops
And they didn't want it
These are very fragile companies with a lot of things missing
And the approach weeaboo is
Teaching is if we make this investment
Is a Rolodex
Strong enough to help these people
So much luck has interviews things
That without it
I think very few of us would have very many successes
One of our investors
Has a very big shareholder
Of Sears and they facilitated the introduction to the buyer at Sears
Where is who would buy a product like this
I think he was
Charms by Nolan and Faye
Found this Explorer
Experiment might be fun
Hong Kong hit the shelves
Just in time for the 1975 Christmas season
Of course
The rest was history
My father is a soul
Proprietor this little candy store
My father was a very Petty Union
Member dad
With a wonderful guy
Yeah and he really encouraged to self
Self-reliance
Little groceries little magazines
Ice cream
Cigarettes
Is a very early age to work there
I clerked I was six years of seven years old
Easier to explain who drove a truck
Then it is to explain what he didn't Union cuz I didn't understand what he didn't you and your other than fight with the head of the Union
And
We used to have a lot of arguments once I understood what a union wasn't and he could not
Couldn't understand why I was so adamantly opposed to the union
It probably
Has to do with money
Deep-seated sense of disappearance
When I was twelve or thirteen I was trying to figure out how to earn some money in the summertime
So I
Said no dad
Maybe
I could sell light bulbs
So I went down to the local Joe
General manager of the
Pennsylvania
Operation
You said your smallest amount that he could sell me would be
Kappa free carpool
Light bulbs
That's why I asked my mother if I could populate our
Basement with all these light bulbs
And I
So I got this wagon
Bigy they can run around and
Sold light bulbs for a whole summer time you called the bright point light bulb
It's a little bit over-the-top but that's what it was
I was a nerd
Highly motivated in patient-driven
Workaholic nerd
Who accidentally became an athlete
Got some sort of social polish
A school for nerds
A mighty
Scramble to get into
Pedigree where I thought I can earn a living which is electronic engineering
I did that for a while and I got us a pretty boring I can't
And I thought well I've heard about business school
Maybe I should take a crack at the
And this is where I got inspired by George dorio
Professor is George Doria with a father figure to a generation of young man at Harvard Business School
This French expatriate had the distinction starting the fur
The First Corporation dedicated exclusively
Exclusively
The Venture investing
American research and development
Founded in 1946
Ironically dorias lasting impact
Would not be through Ard
Which in its entire 25-year history made only one notable investment
Smoke important
Came to the spell he cast over his Harvard classroom
Dory was very controversial
Even at the time
At Harvard
Horse called Manufacturing
Really had nothing to do with Manufacturing
It was extremely popular course and it was all about
Starting companies
And Technology
We talked about on sprinters
Yet some of them must guests
What it was like to start a company
His lectures were
Dress on a drink she should have at a cocktail party
It was sort of George georgiou
Philosophy of life every year he take
One whole session on how to read the New York Times
You should be able to meet this paper in 4 minutes
What did the first section IV
He said now the first thing you want to do is go to the obituary page
There you will learn
The wives that are important
Kind of life that you
Can build for yourself
You would talk about
Working with entrepreneurs and when
X gods
Tough as he always
And you made that point
That he would invite the ashburner over to his home
They have dinner and then you just sit him down in his library in
And play phonograph records of French marching music
And I'll just
You'll with the psychological wounds you know when he was talking about metric Apple starting companies he was as good as
Because he's only thing I understood that I bought it all
Blind singer
What do you mean
At the timer
Started to then take there was no such thing as genetic
Engineering
And to take my idea
Of commercializing
Gene splicing
The wrists were just
Anora
ISO Dwayne of what if
Goddard Arwen
Weather
Make a new life
It was a bet on technology
You looked at the value of the pharmaceutical industry
And if you had a better way
To develop drugs
The power was enormous
Nobody had a clue whether they could pull that off
But you did know
And if they could
It was big
It came
Out of the blue
Blue four
Food for me
I had not been
I've been thinking about
Starting a company
I thought I was going to die at the lab bench where the pie
NY milesplit
Bob called
He wanted to know it's the technology was ready to be commercialized
Bob Swanson
I think
It was the most appreciation
Individual I've ever met
Once you understood
What the potential technology was in genetic engineering
The whole
Way ahead of Antigua
Jim and I were looking around 4
Someone to add to the partnership
And
Bob's reminders
But there just wasn't enough go
What's going on I'm those days amazingly
To really have him full-time working on our Vengeance we don't have that many
But we were interested in doing something
In genetic engineering
We sorta sled
Go there find something new
If you can will finance it if you can
Three is motivated to find something
And he called Professor boyar the University of
Or is it I'll give you 5 minutes
Return in trigonal many hours
In those days
Funding for
Or research was
Difficult
Pencil
No I had some
Ulterior reasons for paying attention when he said he had money
Over the next couple of weeks
Swanson
Persuaded boyar
To take the idea of gene splicing
Intuitive some sort of commercial operation
Voyager 2
So are we go into
One of the
Are Embarcadero towers and we go up to the top floor
Floor
And
You can look out over the world
It was something like out of a movie smoke
Subway
Stern looking guys are sitting there in a suit
Birkin says okay well what are you going to do what are you do what equipment do you need how do you know that you're
How do you test
Scary
What are the risks
Stoop germination
Everything I could think here is this rich guy and all I'm talking to us about science and funding Sinai paid at
At attention
And I didn't know anything about raising money
Of course I knew nothing whatsoever about the technology I mean nobody I had to rely on it cuz it was so much too
Much to be done he was a very Hands-On guy
They wanted to raise
About three million dollars
To build the factory hire the people
And then see if it would work
But underlying at all
Was the
The tremendous risk factor of you know we would it be possible
Pure research
Don't everybody knows if I
Openly fun
Pure research
Somaya and everything is always been to try to
Put the risk up front to get rid of the risk as fast as you possibly can
Mom and I were very naive
About how we were going to do what we did
We changed
Business plan
I persuaded them to
Do it a different way
Subcontract
The experiment
Two different institutions
By subcontracting
Tom Perkins eliminated the need to
Dubai equipment filled elad fire staff
The estimated $3000000 start up cost or reduced
Touchet 250,000
Kleiner Perkins put the money in Tech was in business
Was Bob Swanson in a checkbook
Sitting in our officer
That was genetic
Human insulin
But to Tessa concept it begins a less complex or mode
City of Hope Medical Center in Los Angeles would try to engineer jeans
UT San Francisco
Pick an amount
Afterbirth very long time City of Hope
The nun we transported the Genies
Bob headedness pocket up to University of California and her Boyer
Inserted it into the
Bacterial host
It work so we had our
Another breakthrough
What was the first time in history
Mankind that ever made an artificial
What looks to say an artificial bacteria
Most doctors agree that genetic engineering will be the source of most drugs in the next decade
Play Sia Myriad of products new vaccine we haven't scratched the surface yet in terms of
New harmones and molecules that the body produces itself to keep itself healthy
And I wasn't my goal to start an industry my goal was to
Make sure the science got translated into
An Endeavor that would be used in all the things I've done I think I'm most proud of
Talk because it's well saved
Hundreds of thousands of people's lives
What is the great if you can make money and change the world for the better at the same time
We are now entering our fourth generation of computers
Difficult problems which one's required 30 hours of work by a computer as large as a house canal besaw
I'll be solved in 12 seconds by a computer no bigger than a bathtub
In 1976 the computer was about to get
Personal
Government
Institutions and businesses
Enter the home
For venture capitalist
This represented the opportunity of a lifetime
We turned on Apple computer we didn't we didn't even
Turn it down we agree to meet with Joe
Jobs and Wozniak
Oh that would have been a fabulous and that's what if it made it
But we didn't
We should all know we're not real
Really in that business
Apple music computer helmet
Recipes on it I sent my partner down to look at Apple
He came back and he said the guy kept me waiting for an hour
He's very arrogant
Steve Jobs
Jezebel
Let's not to come
That was big mistake
In 1976
The only people who believed in a personal computer with a sinks in nerds who gathered at Homebrew computer
Computer clubs
At 1 sex club twenty-one-year-old Steve Jobs had partnered with Steve Wozniak
Create a circuit for kids called
The Apple One Steve Jobs with working at REI
The time
Settlement office person to ask for start-up money was his boss Nolan Bushnell
We needed an invalid then the Alchemy a third of a computer for $50,000 and I said
I said cheat I don't think so
I could have owned
The 3rd of Apple computer for $50,000
Big mistake
But I said call Don Valentine
Have high probability of senior opportunity
So we had our meeting
I went to Steve's house and we talked and I was
Convinced
It was a
Big Market
Embryonically beginning
He was in his Foo man Chu look
And his question for me
Tell me
What I have to do to have you feel
I said we have to have someone in the company
Who has some sense of management
And marketing and channels of distribution
Send me three people
I sent him three candidates one he didn't like
One didn't like him
The third one is Mike markkula my part will work for me I'm sure child
Before he went to Intel
He called me up and said there's two guys over on Los Altos today
That. Capri
Really use your help
And you got to go see my souquet
Cuz that's what I did on Mondays
I was retired
I think I was
I retired
Intel
One day week
I would help people start companies and write business plans
I did it for free just from the interaction with bright people that have
It has a lot of fire in her belly
So I went over and talked to the boys
The two of them did not make a good impression on people who aren't they were bearded they didn't smell
Smell good
Pinterest funny
Naive
Waze has designed a really wonderful
Wonderful
Computer
Technology that was really Advanced the problem was
You can walk down the street
During 1976 and talk to 100 people say would you like a personal computer night go what's that
And so I told him I said
Write business plan
So I got to working on it
Gosh you know the opportunity here's just
To pray
The business plants ended with $142,000
We could be cash flow positive
Indictments
Came to the conclusion that we could build a Fortune 500 company in less than 5 years
I said I put up the money that was needed
How do you write a check
Mike markkula.
Came out of retirement
The time in the president and CEO
His first order of business
Build a board of director
In the first call he made
What's the Arthur Rock
Arthur would have missed
Just at Woodward for Mike Martin
Jobs and Wozniak came up to see me
And they were very unappealing
Goatee long hair
Mark Alyssa will before you make up your mind
There's a
Computer show
And you would have come down and see what's going on
And he did
Something what happened he was
Quite sure what
There was a huge Auditorium
And there was a spoof was
Everybody
Around it I couldn't even get next to it
And it was the Apple booth
And it turned out the
Asherah
Bain investment
Then I got a call from Don Valentine this is I want to put the money in that cup I said okay you got to come on the board then
Don's background is
Sales and distribution at the customer satisfaction
Arthur's
Expertise comes from the way the Natural Markets work and how to choose people
I don't think there's a company today because I could say that they had a better board
And that
We couldn't we kind of lose
Take me to place alongside the venture capital
The Luminaries
Was the young Steve Jobs
I would never even seen the inside of a boardroom
Those one board meeting that he took his shoes off and put
Fairfield Vana
Table message
You're excused
Until you can
Come back here that's like a board member
Put shoe back on and everything is fine
He just needed some training in some direction some
Manners
You know in the Venture Capital business if
200 deals and you
You might do 10 of them and you will think they're all great
And if one of them is great
Then you're in the Hall of Fame
If you make 10 deals you know
If you do it well some of them going to succeed summer going to fail using one in there with all the Living Dead moving
Leaving Jazz moving gears resume girls
They don't succeed they don't feel they just sit there and laugh up your time you're too
Rafael for all kinds of reasons
If it's
Struggling to probation to give up
Admit defeat it's always traumatic you get personally involved in these companies
Heartbroken
Just to lose money
You losing money is not a good thing
Programs
Instructions to
To the computer
I can be recorded on floppy disks
In the early 80s
A new kind of company began to attract attention in Silicon Valley
These programs
Call
Dataquest report says there are now twenty seven
Thousand software
Software programs on the market
With a new product being introduced every 11 minutes
I've been listening to Emma's Tex has from software
Office at new Enterprise Associates
Adventure Pro
Cheat code founded
Doctor leaving Arthur
An entrepreneur named Rob Campbell marched in
I was out
Always looking for money
And I was
Flying from Boston to
And I was sitting in the back of the plane and the cheap seats were
Supposed to set
And I noticed
Half the people on the plane
Had their briefcases open
And they had
Overhead transparencies and they were thumbing through them and they were
That really was kind of
The Genesis of why PowerPoint
The way Rob is doing this
And I was
Really impressed with
PowerPoint
You seem shorter automated
Very cumbersome process
And when you see it
Goes right through your bones
So we started finding it
Ceramics firm for by Rob Campbell company
Forethought
With an initial round of funding to develop this
New stocks
The company was getting its venture capitalist
Cause to worry
Any new business
Seldom does what's written in the business
And we had
A multitude of
Limitations of the operating system once invested in trying to develop
Engineering was delayed they were all far
Largest distributor when in the chapter 7 of the bankruptcy
Approach
His partners
Looking for another infusion
Rodkey manager presentation talked about FileMaker talk about what would
It's presentation product was going to be
Nea at higher data
Anu
And
He didn't like it
It ain't like
Company
Me
Lni
My other partner got out of Inception
Basically
Yeah one product where you pay too much in a royalties
And the other one which is not going to work so this isn't worth a dick for saying no
And I said
No more money
Despise Partners doubts
Wasn't ready to let pie
Let PowerPoint go so easily
My mother used to say don't ever underestimate that
Cuz if he takes on challenge
He's going to get it done
Exceptional this presentation product is really a pretty good product
Would you all mind if I did it myself
And they said
Will you can do what you want to do is knock over your conflict as long as we don't have to put any more money yet
So I called
My wife
I said Pam
Stop work in the house
I said I'm going to fun
Fun this company myself
We would never
With dict
Potential problems of the venture
Good if you have a
Serious Pie
Partner good pop
Who's this
I just do
Just don't see this
How can you proceed
As a matter of policy we wouldn't
Permit that Nar place
We have permission
Rubatino
Really hurts
PowerPoint
I remember telling dick I said dick
You didn't make mistake
I thought it would be a million-dollar product right out of the chute
And instead of a billion dollars
How does a shoot
I think we got two and a half to three it was much better than what I hope for
Yeah so I was
Thinking this is enough to validate a public offering
I think Jake would have liked us not to be a choir
He said but you know we really don't have the structure in this company could be a public company
You know I was nervous about access to Capital
He said actually
We've been approached by Microsoft
And they have presentation product but not nearly as good as PowerPoint and it would like to acquire
Choirs who killed their own project I said if that's the way you want to go
Want to go it's okay with me
Another one of
My greatest
Mistakes
Lakes which I have
Mini
Is when Microsoft
Did the acquisition
They wanted to do it all in stock
So I was like you know Microsoft stock has way too much risk
They could dump their stocking us at their pee
Sahara we did an all-cash transaction and don't ask me to calculate what that cause
That cause top of assets to
It's too hurtful
Shmoney
The facts
40%
Of the companies that have
Change Pro
Presidents in 18 months
Tell the young CEOs you're going to work hard and you're going to
If you're lucky you're going to be successful
Firing people is always hard for me
That's a gut-wrenching thing to do if we got to go they got to go I'd rather
The right people in back them then I'm the right idea
An app to change the people
Well nobody plans to do that but those are the facts
So I operational principle that give him a shot help as much a
As much as we can hopefully makes it
Doesn't make it
Off with his head and Aunt for the next guy
In 1984
Cisco Systems with a two-person company
Husband-wife team of Lambeau sack
Sandy Lerner
Cisco was a typical startup
It was certainly run out of our house
Number of
Illustrious companies I think have that distinct
Pisco
Early evangelist
For what would be called internet
The Witcher 1980
Was really just a jury-rigged network of computers use that universities and in the military
A very big problem it allowed the computer systems to talk to each other
First time
Open the door to the development of an online world
It was a desperately-needed product
Woodson and Cisco
We tried from the very beginning to to get funding
We just
Unsuccessful
Not the first
People to see it as
But they sought
Before we did they turned it down
They took the position that
This wasn't a terrible business model
I don't
Taking their position I would have disagreed with that
Physician
The nuts
Clear
Different people
Season differently
The person who got us involved with c
Cisco
You are probably the only person in North America who be willing to deal with these
The people
At Cisco
You were designing hard to get along with p
Got the model right down
Do business with
Totally intolerant of Amistad
Made by anybody
Instrumental
I think so
We were difficult to work with
We were all very independent
We were used to having our own way
I'm certainly there's the mindset that has to go along with
Years and years and years of people say
You can't do what you say you're going to do and you can't
Make money even if you could do it
And that you're the wrong person to do it
We bought a third of the company
For 2.8 million dollars
We had an agreement
You get a third of the company and we get a third of the company and we will fall
The people that run this company
None of us had ever built
We understood that there was an enormous
Need for
For more structure and
To bring in people that we had no way to reach
New role
Recruited John morgridge a veteran several high-tech startups
Cisco
Was George Raft was he
Quarter that I arrived
We hired a shrink
He eliminated fight
Fighting in
Open the open hallways
I actually had the
Vice president engineering
The sales
Is President and why office
We really did have a trench mentality
This is not a good big company mentality
Art kelsa free
On the other hand I think that
There was no one there in that original group who didn't
Ardently loves that company
Esysco Gru
A culture Clash
Developed between employees
And the new hires
Ultimately
This class centered on Sandy Lerner
She was definitely a strong personality
And she definitely was the reason the company existed
Sandy was incredible
Peace in the Paw
The puzzle
Done right
For the customer
Silicon Valley has not always been
Spin the place where
Where the customers thought of
First
Thing me
In some places people thought of second or third
Sandy was ensuring
At the customer's stoto
Unfortunately at the expense
Some of the other major managers
Very much alien needed
The other people in the company
Because
No other than Monday hadn't been there
Very long and
You know I saw them
Right way wrong way
As a people I was trying to protect the
Customers
By your own admission she would detonate
Usually in my office
At Cisco
Intervene the only woman a technical woman
I think I was just very very frightening and
There just wasn't a box for me
And I think that
I didn't make it
Play G-Eazy
For them to ignore me
And I didn't make it
Particularly easy for them to find a suitable box
The box that existed for women at the time
Didn't seem to fit what I thought I would
I was doing
Finally won
My assistant said the
Conference room is
Filled
Cisco employees.
Is demanding to see you
All of the vice presidents of the company were in there
They washed up Sandhill Road and said
Either she goes or we off
Terminator
Or when quitting
August
And he called me and said you want me to handle this and I said no I'll handle it
Sandy was retired
First of all
I'm headed out I was fired
Sean
Call the advance office
He said
You know
You're now worth so much money it really doesn't make any sense
Distance for you to work the
Breakfast hard
I think it's just
A good idea if you just
Retired
What do Heroes
I think I have a
Replacing
In the company and I
I don't really
Once retire right now it was
Pretty Posh yourself
And he said well
I think today is your last day
Mark Lenz office wear
Linen for me that I
Must surely be mistaken
My Stockman's office well Lynnwood have to talk to John
End.
Came back and
Walk out the door with me
We never walk back in
You know this idea that
45% of Founders will be gone in 18 months
In retrospect that was clearly the mindset
Lenin like clearly
Did not understand that that was the game that we were playing you know the first rule Venni game is to know that you're in when
So unpleasant thing to do
The fire anybody
But it's clearly
The Facts of Life
Fake each of the one away with 170 million
I don't know how people think
Of what comes next after the first hundred and seventy million but
I don't think they've ever forgiven either of us
I was once asked did I start Cisco and make a whole bunch of money
It's 45 South. We're probably could look at myself as a mirror in the morning I don't I think I've been a pretty
Pretty good tool user
Emma is a tool
You know technology
Keeps evolving in
But ever since Leonardo DaVinci it's
Evolving and it will continue to revolve
Good times and bad times
It will evolve
Venture capital is here to stay though
My greatest satisfaction out of thinking back on the companies that I've helped start
And help grow
It's nice
Nice to sit in the glow of your adulation but without the entrepreneur
Is your nothing
You have to have these real people with the ideas and their willingness to commit their life
I don't think and I would not say that Silicon Valley is the result of good van
Adventure capitalist not at all
5 m is the main show Venture capitalism Aiden
Sometimes people got lost we must have venture capital
Will you selling Venture Capital unless you have on spinners
But haven't been for the tribe against month
Word Kleiner and I've
Without
Without venture-capital the future wouldn't happen nearly as quickly
New companies are much better displayed in new technology that can extend an idea
We would all have a lower standard living worldwide
And it's early. You know everything from where country code 1
One in the telephone system to the internet
Adventure capital guy going in Turin to a bang
Bank Renee says I want to start delivering mail by chest we going to Kleiner Perkins
We want to make insulin and bacteria he goes okay
Great things don't really come out of the status quo they come out of people with vision
Drive to prove the difference underlying technology was there and
There was nowhere for it to go until another venture capitals up here
Thank Allah we got some money let's take a chance
You need guys with new ideas about how to do think all these
Do something build a company spread
Educate their kids
Do it
What's the temperature